A Guide to the Papers of Virginius Dabney, 1912-1989
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Virginius Dabney, 1912-1989
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7690-al
This collection contains ca. 700 items (3 Hollinger boxes).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Virginius Dabney of Richmond, Virginia, gave this addition to his papers to the Library on January 4, 1990.
Biographical/Historical Information
Virginius Dabney was editor of The Richmond Times-Dispatch.
Scope and Content Information
This addition to the papers of Virginius Dabney (1901- ) of Richmond, Virginia, consists of ca. 700 items, 1912-1989, and comprises research notes, awards, pen and ink drawings, family letters, newsclippings, photographs, printed material and other miscellaneous material.
Two boxes of the collection contain Dabney's research notes for various chapters of his book Virginia Commonwealth University: A Sesquicentennial History.
Dabney received citations and awards from the College of William and Mary, The National Conference of Christians and Jews, the United Daughters of the Confederacy Jefferson Davis Medal and the Wisdom Society.
Letters from Dabney's family, his mother and Aunt Sue, 1945-1955, all pertain to the celebration of his birthday. The majority of the newsclippings are concerned with his activities following his retirement from the editorial page of The Richmond Times-Dispatch in 1969 and include interviews with Dabney, discussions concerning Thomas Jefferson, his association with the Virginia Commonwealth University, honors awarded to Dabney, the Virginia Statute for Religious Freedom, Dumas Malone, and the University of Virginia.
Photographs include those of Dabney and his immediate family, his parents, the Virginia Commonwealth University Board of Trustees and Administrators, Julia and Peter N. Pastore, Charles M. Caravati, the James Branch Cabell Library, the Dabney home, the 75th Raven Society Anniversary Dinner, James Latimer, the Rachel Levy Memorial Tablet at Monticello, Baskerville Bridgeforth at the Giles Robertson's 50th Wedding Anniversary, Dabney at Trillium House, the Times-Dispatch Public Service Awards, Dabney on trips to Moscow, Yucatan, and Barbados, and the Mass Communication Hall of Fame Ceremony.
Printed materials include a catalog, graduation program, and The Monthly Chronicle of the Episcopal High School; a University of Virginia graduation program; publications featuring interviews or talks by Dabney concerning race relations, education, reporters and the election of 1988, and the need for a new Virginia State Library; and programs concerning St. Luke's Annual Pilgrimage Service, the University of Virginia Alumni Hall and Jefferson Room Dedication, "A Literary Evening" at the James Branch Cabell Library, The Virginia Jefferson Meeting on the Constitution, Founder's Day at Longwood College, the Virginia Communications Hall of Fame, the 1986 Douglas Southall Freeman History Award, and a Memorial Service Honoring Ambassador J. Rives Childs.
Other printed items include "Reflections" in The Virginia Magazine of History and Biography; invitations; and Richmond Civil War Round-Table bulletins.
Also present in the collection (see the control folder) is a memorandum, September 28, 1989, by Virginius Dabney concerning the position of the Richmond News-Leader and the Richmond Times-Dispatch concerning interposition and massive resistance during the intergration crisis of the 1950's and comparing their positions with his own editorials at the time. One of the issues over which he disagreed with the management of the papers was the closing of the Prince Edward schools.
Organization
This collection has been divided into two series. Series I consists of the research notes for Dabney's book about the Virginia Commonwealth University. Series II contains all other miscellaneous material.
Contents List
- Research Notes Concerning Virginia Commonwealth University: A Sesquicentennial History
  - Medical College of Virginia, Antebellum and Civil War 1983, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Medical College of Virginia, Postbellum, and Governor Cameron 1984-1985, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Medical College of Virginia, University College of Medicine, and Dr. William H. Taylor 1956, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Medical College of Virginia, Early 1900's, World War I, and Rivalry with the University of Virginia n.d. (Box 1)
  - Medical College of Virginia, Sanger Era (1925-1956), 1968, n.d., (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Medical College of Virginia (1957-1985), 1978, 1983-1986, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Richmond Professional Institute (1917-1967), 1984, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Creation of a University n.d. (Box 2)
  - Nelson - Smith - Temple 1969-1985, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Warren Brandt 1969-1970, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Administration of Edmund Ackell 1982-1986, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Progress in the Eighties - East Campus ca. 1985, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Progress in the Eighties - West Campus ca. 1976-1985, n.d. (Box 2)
  - The Press and Athletics at the Virginia Commonwealth University ca. 1969-1985 (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous Material
  - Awards 1944-1973, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Drawings, Pen and Ink 1957, 1975 (Box 3)
  - Letters from Virginius Dabney's family re his birthday 1945-1955 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Material 1921-1947, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Newsclippings re Virginius Dabney 1913, 1947-1989 (Box 3)
  - Papers re Virginius Dabney by James J. Kilpatrick and Alfred Toombs (Unpublished) 1950, 1985 (Box 3)
  - Photographs 1912-1987, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Printed Material 1917-1988, (2 folders) (Box 3)